A Guide to Materials on Women
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Elizabeth Oakes Smith Papers 1823-1894, 4,000 items.
  The Oakes Smith collection consists of correspondence, diaries, literary manuscripts, essays, lectures, and newspaper columns of Elizabeth Oakes Smith. Also included are the letters and paper of her husband, Seba Smith, their sons and their families, scrapbooks, journals, photographs, and printed items. Mrs. Oakes Smith's extensive correspondence with many literary figures of the day, combined with her succinct essays, lectures and columns on women's rights are the principle strengths of this collection. In addition, her correspondence with her children and grandchildren offer a colorful portrait of family life in the mid to late nineteenth century. #38-707
- Elizabeth Oakes Smith Diary 1861, 1 item.
  Fifty-two page transcript, with notes and 14-page introduction to Elizabeth Oakes Smith's diary for 1861 October-November 8, by Joy Wiltenburg, Excerpts from this transcript were published in Signs: Journal of Women in Culture and Society IX, no. 9, (Summer 1984), 534-548; together with an offprint. #38-707-a
- Elizabeth Oakes Prince Smith Papers 1875-1881, 10 items.
  Primarily letters to Oran S. Baldwin, editor of Baldwin Monthly concerning his magazine and autographs she is sending him. Of interest are manuscripts of her poems "Unattained" and "With the skin of a monkey." In an 1875 letter, she speaks of the courtship of Harriet Beecher and Calvin Stowe; in an 1876 letter she encloses an autograph of Thomas Cole; and in an 1877 letter she speaks of her duties as pastor of an Independent Church in Canostota, New York. #8326-c
- Lotus A. Snow 1948, 1 item.
  Typescript of Ph.D. Dissertation, Imagery in Virginia Woolf's Novels, by Lotus A. Snow. #Microfilm M-; 3564.
- Papers of Richard J. Reid 1770-1920, ca. 2500 items.
  Included is a letter from the sheriff of Marion, Virginia, reporting the capture of a runaway slave who had been travelling with a white woman. The slave had been dressed as a woman and his accomplice as a man. #550
- Stanard Family Papers 1761-1865, 822 items.
  Legal correspondence of Robert Stanard (1781-1846) of Fredericksburg, Spotsylvania County and Richmond, Virginia. His practice was largely concerned with civil suits involving wills, administration of estates, and land matters. There are numerous references to women who seek his help as well as references to slaves. #38-708
- Edward L. Stone Collections 1864-1938, 500,000 items.
  One of the most prominent businessmen in Virginia in the latter half of the 19th century, businesses included Borderland Coal Company and Stone Printing in Roanoke, Virginia. While most of the papers are business in nature there is some personal correspondence with several friends, many women. Also of interest is correspondence between committee members concerning the establishment of a Liberal Arts College for Women. There is correspondence with daughter Mary at her exclusive girls school (Box 229) and after she has married and become a mother (Box 232). #382
- Henry Strickland Journal 1870s, 1 item.
  Henry Strickland, a dealer in groceries and miscellaneous commodities, married Elizabeth Deisher, the widow of George Deisher and took over his business. Items include correspondence with Elizabeth D. Strickland's daughter, May Ann Deisher, as well as depositions regarding George Deisher's estate. #38-20
- Sarah Anne Graves Strickler Fife Diary 1861-1907, 1 item.
  A good portion of this diary is devoted to the Civil War years. Sarah was in her teens during the war years and writes from an Albemarle County school and nearby farm. She wrote little about her family, but much about the war, local troops, and her own appearance and religious views. #5633
- Alexander H. H. Stuart Papers 1791-1928, 500 items.
  Papers pertaining to the career of Alexander Hugh Holmes Stuart (1807-1891), former Secretary of the Interior. In a cryptic letter, July 1791, from Cornelius Baldwin to his newly-married sister, Mrs. Archibald (Betsy) Stuart, he warns her of female malice. Stuart writes his mother, Eleanor Stuart, November 19, 1820-1825, about school life in Williamsburg, Virginia, and living in luxury. He has made several acquaintances, "Particularly amongst the Ladies...[they] are fascinating in their manners...they seem to possess a certain magical influence over you which makes you forget everything else..." Letters from Stuart to his mother during the period of 1850-1853 describes all the social functions he and his wife Fanny are attending in Washington, D.C. In one letter he describes Fanny's new wardrobe in some detail. Another letter of interest, August 18, 1851, is from Susan C. Armstrong, a widowed cousin of Stuart, who implores him for a post in his office, as she has three children to feed and no means left to her. #345
- Stuart-Baldwin Papers 1764-1884, ca. 4500 items.
  Papers, primarily legal, of Archibald Stuart (1757-1832) and Briscoe Gerard Baldwin (1789-1852), lawyers, of Staunton, Virginia. Included are letters from Martha S. Baldwin to her husband, Briscoe G. Baldwin, containing news of family and friends. #228
- Sussex County, Virginia, Miscellaneous Letters 1841, 1853, 1861, 3 items.
  Three miscellaneous letters, Lucy C. Parham to her sister Amanda Parham (January 21, 1841), news to her sister who is in Maryland, implores her to visit, talks about a visitor from a Northern city who was neglecting her new baby and thinks this is typical of city women character, Carrie writes to Mollie about teaching and religion in the two remaining letters. (July 31, 1853 and October 1859). #38-431
- Thomas White Sydnor Papers 1825-1890, ca. 7000 items.
  Baptist minister and educator. Correspondence, printed matter and other papers dealing with general, social, religious, and educational conditions in the counties of King and Queen and Nottaway, Virginia, where Sydnor was superintendent of schools. Includes Elementary lessons in English, pt. 1, by Nelly Lloyd Knox Heath (1880). Names of schools mentioned in the collection include Danville Female College, Danville, Virginia; George Washington University, Washington, D.C.; Hollins College, Hollins, Virginia; and the University of Richmond. #38-146
- Tayloe Family Papers 1756-1893, ca. 300 items.
  Papers of the King George County, Virginia family, primarily Henry A. Benjamin Ogle, and Edward Thornton Tayloe. An indenture, dated December 2, 1822, related the conveyence of a "Mulatto" girl to Henrietta Key; and several property transactions involving women are of interest. #38-630.
- Charles Elisha Taylor 1860-1890, 200 items.
  Letters of Charles Elisha Taylor of Richmond, Virginia, concerning his Civil War experience, especially to his mother and sister. Letters after the war concern women, especially their role in the Baptist Church in Richmond. Also included in the collection is the 15-page diary, 1865, of Mary Elisha Taylor, revealing some concern for the war. #3091
- Margaret and Olivia Taylor Photographs 1977, 7 items.
  Taken in April and May, these photographs are mostly of the Misses Margaret Randolph and Olivia Alexander Taylor at their residence in Albemarle County, Virginia, "Lochlyn." and other local areas. Miss Margaret (June 9, 1888-April 1, 1985) and Miss Olivia (October 31, 1890-April 3 1985) were the great-great-great granddaughters of Thomas Jefferson through the line of their father, Stevens Mason Taylor of "Tuckahoe." Both ladies received bachelor degrees from George Washington University and pursued teaching careers at Western High School in Georgetown and Eastern High School in Washington, D.C., respectively. #8937-d
- John Reuben Thompson Papers 1842-1926, ca. 500 items.
  The correspondence, poems, speeches, Civil War material, news articles and essays of this editor of Southern Literary Messenger and New York Evening Post. Correspondents include Mary Barker Carter Dodge, Susan P. Thompson Quarles (his sister), Anne Isabella Thackeray, and Elizabeth Drew Barstow Stoddard. #38-705
- William Thornton Papers 1860-1963, 9 boxes
  The papers of Dean William Thornton of the University of Virginia, including the letters of the Janet Thornton, one of the pioneers in the field of medical social work. Also included are her recollections and newspapers clippings about her. In addition there are the diaries, notebooks, and passport of Eliza Carter Thurman. #2077-e
- Abigail Brown Tompkins 1922, 1 item.
  A watercolor, 2"x3", entitled "The Country Ford, Ideal new Jersey Autumn Scene." #38-758
- Maria Ball Carter Tucker 1815-1819, 1 item.
  Typescript of the Commonplace book of Maria Tucker. #38-522
- Maria R. F. Tucker Letter 1825, 1 item.
  Tucker thanks Harriet Douglas for a hat and mentions her reluctance to leave Lynchburg, a call by the ladies from Monticello, their pavilion, and family news including a marriage to a nephew of General Jackson, in this letter of July 12, 1825. #10579
- Nathaniel Beverly Tucker Papers 1857-1861, ca. 100 items.
  Letters between Tucker and his relatives while Tucker was serving as consul in Liverpool, England, from 1851-1861. The letters from Virginia were mainly from relatives at Tucker's home in Jefferson County. Included is a January 30, 1853, letter stating that the slave "Mammy" requests that she be taken to her grave in a hearse. #10321
- Randolph Beverly Tucker Collection 1833, 4 items.
  Includes Mary Sherlock's receipt of lands granted to her father, Captain Samuel Timpson for his military service and her affidavit regarding disposition of the land. #5668
- Nancy Byrd Turner 1939, 1 item.
  Uncorrected galley proof of George Washington's Mother. #411
- Twyman Family Papers 1750-1911, ca. 60 items.
  Twyman family of Albemarle and Louisa counties, Virginia. Includes scattered correspondence from women members of the family. Of special interest is a letter, n.d., G.T. to Joseph Twyman, where he writes about women "as the devil's tools." #38-153
- Twyman Family Papers ca. 1790-1890, 300 items.
  Business, legal, and personal papers of the Albemarle County, Virginia family. Included is a February 15, 1838 letter from George Twyman to his brother and mother in which he mentions hearing that they have lost a female slave and her baby. #7808
- United Daughters of the Confederacy 1941, 1 item.
  Minutes of the 46th annual of Virginia Division of the U.D.C. held in Bristol, Virginia in 1941. #1349
- United Daughters of the Confederacy 1939, 1948, 2 items.
  Report of the President General-United Daughters of the Confederacy 1939, as well as typed notes, 1948, by Mrs. Walter D. Lamar, President. #3078
- University of Virginia 1966-1970, 3 boxes
  Material concerning the admission of women to the University of Virginia. Includes reports, correspondence, statistics, minutes, tables, surveys, and institutional analyses. #RG 20/53
- Queen Victoria Letter 1866, 1 item.
  Facsimile of a letter, March 28, 1866, from Queen Victoria, Windsor Castle, to George Peabody (1795-1869), thanking him for his munificent aid to her poorer subjects living in London, and saying that she would have a miniature portrait of herself painted for him. #3661
- Virginia Business Accounts 1813-1898, 17 ledgers
  Seventeen bound volumes from businesses in Richmond and Petersburg, Virginia. Of interest is the John and Joseph Wilder ledger of Petersburg (1793-1803) which includes some accounts for women, also the ledger from Buchanan V. Pollek's general store in Petersburg (1806-1820) contains accounts for women. #2135
- Virginia Music Festival Papers 1947-1948, 42 items.
  Correspondence and records of the Virginia Music Festival. Correspondents include Hannah Catlin; Mary Ely Lyman, Dean of Sweet Briar College; Jean Bird; Marion Chauncey of Mary Washington College; and Edna T. Shaeffer. #3628
- Virginia Quarterly Review 1925-1955, 188 boxes
  Consists of the editorial correspondence, proofs, and manuscripts of this literary publication. Numerous women, both authors and scholars, are represented in the collection. #RG-24/3/1.391, RG-24/3/1.561
- Betty Walker School Teacher's Account Book 1834-1866, 1 item.
  Typescript of school teacher's account book, 1834-1866, kept by Miss Betty Walker for Nottoway County, Virginia. #2265
- Wallace Family Papers 1750-1864, ca. 115 items.
  Primarily the papers of Doctor Michael Wallace and his six sons of King George County, Virginia. Of special interest are the letters of Michael Wallace, Dr. Wallace's son, concerning a suit over a slave family. The suit was over counter claims on a female slave. Also of interest are the wills mentioning women, and a letter, October 3, 1785, George Hooe to Michael Wallace, requesting that he "inquire of Grace Grigsby of the marriage of Mrs. Barnes daughters, who married against the will of their father." Also a letter dated April 8, 1775, James Wallace to Michael Wallace, not to delay his attentions to a certain young lady as "ladies in general on this side the River (Potomac) are very abrupt in matrimonial affairs." #38-150
- Wallace, Rogers, Woodson and Carter Families 1799-1884, ca. 210 items.
  Assorted correspondence of members of these families of Albemarle and Goochland counties, Virginia. Of interest are the letters of Deborah Logan, of Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, to her niece, Deborah Norris Woodson, Goochland County, Virginia. Of interest are the letters of Deborah Logan, of Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, to her niece, Deborah Norris Woodson, Goochland County, Virginia. In a letter dated July 2, 1829, D. L. writes D. N. W., "for the concentration of great and sensible men...from Virginia, have given a very general idea of the genius of her sons, how can we suppose in her care alone, that nature is the same letter she speaks of Fanny who is stricken with a "palsey" in a new town "Where she is unknown and so many of her colour are very wretched." A letter from D.L. to D.N.W., January 18, 1829, encourages her to read "useful and sensible books, not exclusively novels," and agreeable one's now adorn literature of the day, both in Europe and America." Later she mentioned Fanny again who is now in Philadelphia," the misery of the coloured population is so great in the suburb of the city...to make any kind heart regret they are no longer under the protection of those more competent...yet I am an enemy of slavery and should be very glad if it did not exist among us." In letters dated 1829-1830, D.L. writes of Mrs. Madison, Mrs. Monroe, and Martha Jefferson Randolph, of a cholera epidemic in Philadelphia, the Nat Turner revolt and her concern about the South and slavery. On a more personal level she stresses education and reading for women and her views on politics. The former slave Fanny is visited by her son who is doing quite well in Haiti. She also mentions in a letter dated March 12, she writes of a terrible thunderstorm the tragedy which resulted," a poor young woman at a factory a few miles from us...she was sitting at her loom near the end of the building which was struck by lightening, a large iron bolt of the machinery was just above her from whence attracted by the steel in her corset bosom it instantly killed and tore her poor body with frightful violence." Letters dated 1833-1835 from D. L. to D. N. W. concern the South and Nullification, John Randolph of Roanoke, vehemently opposes Martin Van Buren and other leaders. On a more intimate level she writes of a woman eloping and marrying beneath her station, she had clandestine meetings with the man, she writes often of her friend Sarah Walker whose husband or father is a tyrant, and in a letter dated June 3, 1933, D. L. writes "good housewifery is a very important part of the character of a woman." A very strong set of letters from an opinionated woman. #2689
- Washington-Lewis-Madison Papers 18th-19th century, ca. 590 items.
  Part of the Tracy William MacGregor Library. Prominent families of Virginia, includes some scattered correspondence from women. #2988.
- Mary Washington Will May 1788, 1 item.
  Photograph copy of the Will of Mary Washington. #38-554
- Watson Family Papers 1750-1926, 24,215 items.
  A superb collection pertaining to plantation life, consisting of the papers of Garritt Minor (d. 1799), David Watson (1773-1830), and Thomas Watson (1819-1895). The papers of Garrett Minor of Louisa and Spotsylvania counties, Virginia, include personal correspondence with his wife Mary, his brothers and their widows and his children. Papers of David Watson, son-in-law of Garrett Minor, touch on philosophy, law, and romance of his youth to letters regarding the loss of children and correspondence between him and his wife Sally. There is also substantial correspondence between Mrs. Sally Watson and Dr. James Watson and Thomas Watson (1830-1841). #530
- Waugh Family Letter 1825, 1 item.
  An examination, April 19, 1825, of Rachel and Catherine Waugh (sisters-in-law), in regards to a deed, Washington, D. C. #3079
- Webb-Prentis Papers 1770-1907, ca. 10,000 items.
  Financial, personal and legal papers of the Webb-Prentis families of Suffolk and Williamsburg, Virginia. Very strong in ante-bellum correspondence among women and relatives. Of special interest are the letters of Elizabeth Bowdoin Prentis (1791-1859) to her brother Joseph Prentis and others. #4136
- Whitman-Oakes Smith Collection 1846-1857, 1875, n.d., 21 items.
  Mostly letters (photocopies) from John Neal, Portland, Maine, to Mrs. Elizabeth Oakes Smith, New York. #38-311
- John Wickham Papers 1784-1880, 3 microfilm reels
  Diaries, journals, and letters of John Wickham relating to his law practice in Richmond and Williamsburg, Virginia, the defense of Aaron Burr, farm accounts and personal affairs. Included are letters, 1818- 1831, to John Wickham from Miss M. M. Fanning; letters, 1819-1835, to John Wickham from his wife and sons; letters, 1794-1799, to Elizabeth McLurg from Littleton W. Tazewell, Edwin and William Burwell, and others; and letters, 1805-1841, to Elizabeth S. (Mrs. John) Wickham from John Wickham, James Wickham, and various other relatives and individuals. #409
- Mrs. Wilhelmina Ashlin White Papers 1843-1866, 267 items.
  Personal correspondence of this Lexington woman who attended a girls school in Charlottesville, Virginia. #9762
- Sarah Helen Whitman 1872, 1905, 2 items
  Letter from Sarah Helen Whitman to William Whitman Bailey discussing his work in the Atlantic and his 15-page recollection of her entitled, "Recollections of Sarah Helen Whitman." #774
- Adele Williams 1910, 1 item.
  Oil portrait of Edward Wilson James by Adele Williams #38-402-b
- Joan Williams Letters 1984, 2 items.
  Williams writes to Mary Preston Massey, Keswick, Virginia on April 24, 1984, saying that she is coming to Charlottesville for the PEN Faulkner award ceremony and that she has won a Guggenheim with Nancy Hale's help. The May 1984 letter thanks Mrs. Massie for courtesies during Williams' visit. #9394-e
- Williams Family 1840s-1920s, 30 items.
  Of interest is a sale document, December 5, 1843, for a slave girl named Henrietta, aged fourteen years. #2480
- James Southall Wilson Papers 1931, 75 items.
  Letters addressed to Wilson by 44 distinguished Southern authors invited to attend a Southern Writers Convention. Included are Katharine Anthony, Emily Clark Balch, Willa Cather, Ellen Glasgow, Sara Haardt, Mary Johnston, Margaret Prescott Montague, Julia Peterkin, Josephine Pinckney, Lizaette Woodworth Reese, Alice Caldwell Hegan Rice, Elizabeth Maddox Roberts, Helen Stallings, and Amelie Rives Troubetzkoy. The letters are often concerned with the writing profession from the author's point of view. #38-428
- James Southall Wilson Collection 1921-1976, 56 items.
  Consists chiefly of letters from Margaret and James Branch Cabell, Willa Cather, Donald Davidson, Ellen Glasgow, DuBose and Dorothy Heyward, and Walter de la Mare to University of Virginia English Professor James Southall Wilson (1880-1963) and wife Julia. The letters from James Branch Cabell (1879-1958) and his wife Margaret congratulate Wilson and discuss personal and literary matters. A single letter of Willa Cather (1873-1947) to Mr. [Stringfellow] Barr responds negatively to an invitation to lecture at the University of Virginia due to unsettled family conditions, although she says that "I always feel very deeply that I am a Virginian" (December 5, 1928). Ellen Glasgow also discusses literary and personal news. Dorothy Heyward speaks of going to the Huntington Hartford Foundation for writers in order to finish a book begun in summer (January 14, 1960). #7436-e
- Susan Colston Wilson Papers 1880-1945, 1500 items.
  The daughter of John Wilson and Susan Colston Minor Wilson (see Minor-Wilson papers), Susan was born in Pennsylvania and attended private schools in Virginia. She was trained in occupational therapy work in New York and from 1918-1919 served as a reconstruction aide in France and the U.S. In 1924, she became the Chief Occupational Therapist at the Brooklyn State Hospital. In the early forties she was a lecturer on occupational therapy at NYU and soon became an occupational therapy officer at the U.S. Naval Hospital in Seattle, Washington. The events in her life are well documented in letters, particularly to her mother, and numerous photographs. Also included is correspondence of her siblings, and parents. A strong collection for 19th century family life. #10489
- Wirt-Carrington 1819-1831, 1 item.
  A 300-page volume containing typescript letters from Laura H. Wirt, daughter of William Wirt, Attorney General of the United States, to Louisa Cabell Carrington, Laura Wirt's mother, Elizabeth Wirt, was the sister of Louisa Cabell Carrington's step-mother, Agnes S. B. Gamble Cabell. Louisa married Henry Carrington in 1820, bore eight children and died January 8, 1865. Laura Wirt married Thomas Randall in 1827, bore four daughters and died in Florida in 1834. They shared confidences and gossip. Laura's letters are sparkling and witty and touch upon all the current events, music, literature, health, romance, and family. Her letters are extremely frank in nature. For example in writing to Louisa after her marriage and after her move to Florida, she writes "it requires some time, however, for a nouvelle mariee to learn to be happy under the change of circumstances...I never was less happy in my life than the two first two months of my marriage...I love him [Thomas Randall, her husband] very much, Louisa. Even more than when he was my lover...a lover is more charming than a husband, but not so dear. No doubt it is the same case with us women, and perhaps we gain as much as we lose by the exchange" (March 6, 1828). A strong collection which reflects relationships which women had with each other. #2546
- Withrow Family Papers 1870-1925, ca. 1000 items.
  Letters to William Withrow, Jr. and his wife, Mary Anne Jones Withrow of Waynesboro, Virginia, from their children, relatives, and acquaintance. His daughter Evelyn married Matthew Hale Houston, a Presbyterian missionary to China, in 1871. Letters concerning the Houstons' stay at the Presbyterian Mission Church in Hangchow include the following: January 4, August 11, and September 6, 1881; March 22, August 5 & 12, September 13, October 3 & 16, and November 18, 1882. Louisa and her brother Charles, a graduate of the University of Virginia, were both educators, and their correspondence at times discusses their work. #38-148
- Women Authors in Virginia Notes 1940, 2 items.
  Two loose-leaf binders, containing bibliographical and biographical notes on women authors in Virginia. #2766
- Waddy Butler Wood Papers 1918-1934, 131 items.
  Copies of floor plans, designs and photographs of the Department of the Interior Building and other Washington, D.C. buildings designed by Waddy Butler Wood. Included are plans for Government Dormitories for Women. #2468-b